Bibliography

This bibliography is a collection of academic work on data physicalization. You can help us extend it.

For work that does not refer to data physicalization but describes technologies which may be used for that purpose, see technologies. For non-academic work, see the list of physical visualizations.

Please do not link to articles behind paywalls. If you authored an article for which no link is available, please put your PDF online and send us the link. The principle of self-archiving generally allows you to do so.

Peer-reviewed full papers

2023

Dennis Peeters, Champika Ranasinghe, Auriol Degbelo & Faizan Ahmed.
EmoClock: Communicating Real-Time Emotional States Through Data Physicalizations.
In: Proc. of INTERACT 2023. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 14142. Springer, Cham.
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-42280-5_26

C. M. Epa Ranasinghe, Degbelo, A.
Encoding Variables, Evaluation Criteria, and Evaluation Methods for Data Physicalisations: A Review.
Multimodal Technologies and Interaction, 7(7), 73.
https://www.mdpi.com/2414-4088/7/7/73

Eva Hornecker, Trevor Hogan, Uta Hinrichs, and Rosa van Koningsbruggen.
A Design Vocabulary for Data Physicalization.
ACM ToCHI (Transactions Computer-Human Interaction). Just Accepted (August 2023). 58 pages (just accepted version)
https://doi.org/10.1145/3617366

Lee Jones, Greta Grip, and Sara Nabil.
Wear Your Heart on Your Sleeve: Using Digital Knitting Machines to Craft Wearable Biodata Portraits.
In Proceedings of the 2023 ACM Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS '23). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 547–563.
https://doi.org/10.1145/3563657.3596007

Michael J. McGuffin, Ryan Servera, and Marie Forest.
Path Tracing in 2D, 3D, and Physicalized Networks.
In the IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10024310

Kim Sauvé, Pierre Dragicevic, and Yvonne Jansen.
Edo: A Participatory Data Physicalization on the Climate Impact of Dietary Choices.
In Proceedings of the Seventeenth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction (TEI '23). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 35, 1–13.
https://doi.org/10.1145/3569009.3572807

2022

Žarko Dumičić, Katja Thoring, Hermann W Klöckner, and Gesche Joost.
Design elements in data physicalization: A systematic literature review.
DRS 2022 Proceedings. Design Research Society

Bae, S. Sandra, Clement Zheng, Mary Etta West, Ellen Yi-Luen Do, Samuel Huron, and Danielle Albers Szafir.
Making Data Tangible: A Cross-disciplinary Design Space for Data Physicalization.
In: Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New Orleans, Louisana, 2022.

Rosa van Koningsbruggen, Hannes Waldschütz, and Eva Hornecker.
What is Data? - Exploring the Meaning of Data in Data Physicalisation Teaching.
In Sixteenth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction (TEI '22). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 13, 1–21.
https://doi.org/10.1145/3490149.3501319

Kim Sauvé, Miriam Sturdee, and Steven Houben.
Physecology: A Conceptual Framework to Describe Data Physicalizations in their Real-World Context.
ACM Trans. Comput.-Hum. Interact. 29, 3, Article 27 (June 2022), 33 pages. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3505590

Brigitte Stegers, Kim Sauvé, and Steven Houben.
Ecorbis: A Data Sculpture of Environmental Behavior in the Home Context.
In Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS '22). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 1669–1683. https://doi.org/10.1145/3532106.3533508

2021

Maria Karyda, Danielle Wilde, and Mette Gislev Kjarsgaard.
Narrative physicalization: Supporting interactive engagement with personal data.
IEEE Comput. Graph. Appl. 41, 1 (Jan. 2021), 74–86

Charles Perin
What Students Learn with Personal Data Physicalization
IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications, vol. 41, no. 06, pp. 48-58, 2021. DOI: 10.1109/MCG.2021.3115417

Bridger Herman, Maxwell Omdal, Stephanie Zeller, Clara A. Richter, Francesca Samsel, Greg Abram, and Daniel F. Keefe.
Multi-Touch Querying on Data Physicalizations in Immersive AR.
Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 5, ISS, Article 497 (November 2021), 20 pages. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1145/3488542

Laura J. Perovich, Sara Ann Wylie, Roseann Bongiovanni
Chemicals in the Creek: designing a situated data physicalization of open government data with the community
IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Volume: 27, Issue: 2, Feb. 2021), DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2020.3030472

H. Djavaherpour1, F. Samavati1, A. Mahdavi-Amiri2, F. Yazdanbakhsh1, S. Huron3, R. Levy1, Y. Jansen4, and L. Oehlberg
Data to Physicalization: A Survey of the Physical Rendering Process.
EUROVIS 2021 Volume 40 (2021), Number 3. STAR – State of The Art Report. Computer Graphics Forum © 2021 John Wiley & Sons Ltd.

Daphne Menheere, Evianne van Hartingsveldt, Mads Birkebæk, Steven Vos, and Carine Lallemand.
Laina: Dynamic Data Physicalization for Slow Exercising Feedback.
Proc. of Designing Interactive Systems 2021 (DIS '21). ACM NY, USA, 1015–1030. DOI:https://doi.org/10.1145/3461778.3462041

Florian ‘Floyd’ Mueller, Rohit Khot, Tim Dwyer, Sarah Goodwin, Kim Marriott, Jialin Deng, Han Phan, Jionghao Lin, Kun-Ting Chen, and Yan Wang.
Data as Delight: Eating data
Proceedings of CHI 2021, ACM NY, USA, Article 621. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3411764.3445218

Kim Sauvé, David Verweij, Jason Alexander, and Steven Houben
Reconfiguration Strategies with Composite Data Physicalizations.
Proceedings of CHI 2021, ACM NY, USA, Article 471. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3411764.3445746

Adam Drogemuller, Andrew Cunningham, James Walsh, James Baumeister, Ross T. Smith, and Bruce H. Thomas.
Haptic and Visual Comprehension of a 2D Graph Layout Through Physicalisation
Proc. of CHI 2021, ACM, NY, https://doi.org/10.1145/3411764.3445704

Irene López García and Eva Hornecker.
Scaling Data Physicalization – How Does Size Influence Experience?
Proc. of 2021 ACM on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction Conference (TEI’ 21) ACM, NY,

2020

D. Lockton, L. Forlano, J. Fass and L. Brawley
Thinking With Things: Landscapes, Connections, and Performances as Modes of Building Shared Understanding
In IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications, vol. 40, no. 6, pp. 38-50, 1 Nov.-Dec. 2020, doi: 10.1109/MCG.2020.3027591.

Sauvé, Kim, Saskia Bakker, and Steven Houben.
Econundrum: Visualizing the climate impact of dietary choice through a shared data sculpture.
In Proceedings of the 2020 ACM Designing Interactive Systems Conference, pp. 1287-1300. 2020. DOI: 10.1145/3357236.3395509

Friske, Mikhaila, Jordan Wirfs-Brock, and Laura Devendorf.
Entangling the roles of maker and interpreter in interpersonal data narratives: Explorations in yarn and sound.
In Proceedings of the 2020 ACM Designing Interactive Systems Conference, pp. 297-310. 2020. DOI: 10.1145/3357236.3395442

Karyda, Maria, Merja Ryöppy, Jacob Buur, and Andrés Lucero.
Imagining Data-Objects for Reflective Self-Tracking.
In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pp. 1-12. 2020. DOI: 10.1145/3313831.3376844

Kirshenbaum, Nurit, James Hutchison, Ryan Theriot, Dylan Kobayashi, and Jason Leigh.
Data in context: Engaging audiences with 3D physical geo-visualization.
In Extended Abstracts of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pp. 1-9. 2020. DOI: 10.1145/3334480.3382968

Panagiotidou, Georgia, Sinem Görücü, and Andrew Vande Moere.
Data Badges: Making an academic profile through a DIY wearable physicalization.
IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications 40, no. 6 (2020): 51-60. DOI: 10.1109/MCG.2020.3025504

Raidou, Renata G., M. Eduard Gröller, and Hsiang‐Yun Wu.
Slice and Dice: A Physicalization Workflow for Anatomical Edutainment.
In Computer Graphics Forum, vol. 39, no. 7, pp. 623-634. 2020. DOI: 10.1111/cgf.14173

Perovich, Laura J., Phoebe Cai, Amber Guo, Kristin Zimmerman, Katherine Paseman, Dayanna Espinoza Silva, and Julia G. Brody.
Data Clothing and BigBarChart: designing physical data reports on indoor pollutants for individuals and communities.
IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications 41, no. 1 (2020): 87-98. DOI: 10.1109/MCG.2020.3025322.

Khot, Rohit Ashok, Larissa Hjorth, and Florian Mueller.
Shelfie: a framework for designing material representations of physical activity data.
ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI) 27, no. 3 (2020): 1-52.

Beghelli, Alejandra, Gonzalo Huerta-Cánepa, and Ricardo Segal.
Data materialisation: a new undergraduate course for a data driven society.
In Proceedings of the Design Society: International Conference on Engineering Design, vol. 1, no. 1, pp. 2061-2070. Cambridge University Press, 2019.

Kurtis Danyluk, Teoman Tomo Ulusoy, Wei Wei, and Wesley Willett.
Touch and Beyond:Comparing Physical and Virtual Reality Visualizations.
IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, doi: 10.1109/TVCG.2020.3023336.

Maria Karyda, Merja Ryöppy, Jacob Buur, and Andrés Lucero.
Imagining Data-Objects for Reflective Self-Tracking.
In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 1–12.

Dietmar Offenhuber.
What We Talk About When We Talk About Data Physicality
in IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications, vol. 40, no. 6, pp. 25-37, 1 Nov.-Dec. 2020

Kim Sauvé, Dominic Potts, Jason Alexander, and Steven Houben.
A Change of Perspective: How User Orientation Influences the Perception of Physicalizations.
In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 1–12.

Kim Sauvé, Saskia Bakker, Nicolai Marquardt, and Steven Houben.
LOOP: Exploring Physicalization of Activity Tracking Data.
In Proceedings of the 11th Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction: Shaping Experiences, Shaping Society (NordiCHI '20). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 52, 1–12.

M. Karyda, D. Wilde and M. G. Kjærsgaard.
Narrative Physicalization: Supporting Interactive Engagement With Personal Data
in IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications, vol. 41, no. 1, pp. 74-86, 1 Jan.-Feb.

Annemiek Veldhuis, Rong-Hao Liang, and Tilde Bekker.
CoDa: Collaborative Data Interpretation Through an Interactive Tangible Scatterplot. In Proceedings of the Fourteenth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction (TEI '20). ACM NY, 323–336.

Jörn Hurtienne, Franzisca Maas, Astrid Carolus, Daniel Reinhardt, Cordula Baur, and Carolin Wienrich.
Move&Find: The Value of Kinaesthetic Experience in a Casual Data Representation
In IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications, vol. 40, no. 6, pp. 61-75, 1 Nov.-Dec. 2020, doi: 10.1109/MCG.2020.3025385.

2019

Ang, Kathleen D., Faramarz F. Samavati, Samin Sabokrohiyeh, Julio Garcia, and Mohammed S. Elbaz.
Physicalizing cardiac blood flow data via 3D printing.
Computers & Graphics 85 (2019): 42-54. DOI: 10.1016/j.cag.2019.09.004

Mathieu Le Goc, Charles Perin, Sean Follmer, Jean-Daniel Fekete and Pierre Dragicevic.
Dynamic Composite Data Physicalization Using Wheeled Micro-Robots".
IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 25, no. 1, pp. 737-747.

Yun Wang, Adrien Segal, Roberta Klatsky, Daniel F. Keefe, Petra Isenberg, Jörn Hurtienne, Eva Hornecker, Tim Dwyer and Stephen Barrass.
DOI:10.1109/MCG.2019.2923483 An Emotional Response to the Value of Visualization**
IEEE Computer Graphics & Applications Magazine, Visualization Viewpoints, Volume: 39, Issue:5, 2019. pp. 8-17.

Audrey Desjardins and Timea Tihanyi.
ListeningCups: A Case of Data Tactility and Data Stories.
In Proceedings of the 2019 on Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS '19). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 147–160.

David Verweij, David Kirk, Kay Rogage, and Abigail Durrant.
Domestic widgets: Leveraging household creativity in co-creating data physicalisations.
RTD Conference

2018

Courtney Starrett, Susan Reiser, and Tom Pacio.
Data Materialization: A Hybrid Process of Crafting a Teapot.. In ACM SIGGRAPH 2018 Art Gallery (Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada) (SIGGRAPH ’18). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 381–385.

Xiuming Zhang, Tali Dekel, Tianfan Xue, Andrew Owens, Qiurui He, Jiajun Wu, Stefanie Mueller and William T. Freeman.
MoSculp: Interactive Visualization of Shape and Time.
UIST 2018 - In Proceedings of the 31th Annual Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology.

Mathieu Le Goc, Charles Perin, Sean Follmer, Jean-Daniel Fekete, and Pierre Dragicevic.
Dynamic Composite Data Physicalization Using Wheeled Micro-Robots.
TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

Christoph Bader, Dominik Kolb, James C. Weaver, Sunanda Sharma, Ahmed Hosny, João Costa, and Neri Oxman.
Making data matter: Voxel printing for the digital fabrication of data across scales and domains.
Science Advances 4.5 (2018)

Dario Rodighiero
Printing Walkable Visualizations.
TI 2018 - Proceedings of the 5th Biennial Transdisciplinary Imaging Conference 2018.

Kellyann Geurts
Imagining Thought in Digital Space: 3D Printed Thoughts.
TI 2018 - Proceedings of the 5th Biennial Transdisciplinary Imaging Conference 2018.

Alice Thudt, Uta Hinrichs, Samuel Huron and Sheelagh Carpendale.
Self-reflection and personal physicalization construction.
CHI 2018 - Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2018.

Marinos Koutsomichalis.
Objektivisering: Text Physicalization and Self-introspective Post-digital Objecthood.
TEI 2018 - Proceedings of the Twelfth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction.

Ricardo Sosa, Victoria Gerrard, Antonio Esparza, Rebeca Torres, Robbie Napper.
Data Objects: Design Principles for Data Physicalization.
DESIGN 2018 - International Design Conference.

Noura Howell, John Chuang, Abigail De Kosnik, Greg Niemeyer, Kimiko Ryokai
Emotional Biosensing: Exploring Critical Alternatives.
CSCW 2018

2017

Pon, Aura, Eric Pattison, Lawrence Fyfe, Laurie Radford, and Sheelagh Carpendale.
Torrent: Integrating embodiment, physicalization and musification in music-making.
In Proceedings of the Eleventh International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction, pp. 209-216. 2017. DOI: 10.1145/3024969.3024974

Khot, Rohit Ashok, Deepti Aggarwal, Ryan Pennings, Larissa Hjorth, and Florian 'Floyd' Mueller.
Edipulse: investigating a playful approach to self-monitoring through 3D printed chocolate treats.
In Proceedings of the 2017 CHI conference on human factors in computing systems, pp. 6593-6607. 2017. DOI: 10.1145/3025453.3025980

Khot, Rohit Ashok, Simon Stusak, Andreas Butz, and Florian 'Floyd' Mueller.
10 design themes for creating 3D printed physical representations of physical activity data. In IFIP Conference on Human-Computer Interaction, pp. 85-105. Springer, Cham, 2017.

Deborah Lupton.
Feeling your data: Touch and making sense of personal digital data.
New Media & Society. July 2017.

Alberto Boem and Hiroo Iwata.
"It's like holding a human heart": the design of Vital + Morph, a shape-changing interface for remote monitoring.
AI & Society: Knowledge, Culture and Communication. 1435-5655.

Eslam Nofal, Rabee Reffat, and Andrew Vande Moere.
Phygital|Heritage: an Approach for Heritage Communication.
Proceedings of the Third Immersive Learning Research Network Conference. Verlag der Technischen Universität Graz, 2017.

Louis Thibault and François Bérard.
The Object Inside: Assessing 3D Examination with a Spherical Handheld Perspective-Corrected Display.
CHI 2017 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2017.

Wesley Willett, Yvonne Jansen, and Pierre Dragicevic.
Embedded Data Representations.
TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 23.1 (2017): 461-470.

Faisal Taher, Yvonne Jansen, Jonathan Woodruff, John Hardy, Kasper Hornbæk, and Jason Alexander.
Investigating the Use of a Dynamic Physical Bar Chart for Data Exploration and Presentation.
TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 23.1 (2017): 451-460.

Sergej Stoppel and Stefan Bruckner.
Vol²velle: Printable Interactive Volume Visualization.
TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 23.1 (2017): 861-870.

Carmen Hull and Wesley Willett.
Building with Data: Architectural Models as Inspiration for Data Physicalization.
In Proceedings of the 2017 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '17). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 1217–1264.

2016

Yvonne Jansen, Kasper Hornbæk.
A Psychophysical Investigation of Size as Physical Variable.
TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, 22:1. IEEE, 2016.

Steven Houben, Connie Golsteijn, Sarah Gallacher, Rose Johnson, Saskia Bakker, Nicolai Marquardt, Licia Capra and Yvonne Rogers.
Physikit: Data Engagement Through Physical Ambient Visualizations in the Home.
CHI 2016 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2016.

Saiganesh Swaminathan, Thijs Roumen, Robert Kovacs, David Stangl, Stefanie Mueller, and Patrick Baudisch.
Linespace: A Sensemaking Platform for the Blind
CHI 2016 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2016.

Mathieu Le Goc, Lawrence H. Kim, Ali Parsaei, Jean-Daniel Fekete, Pierre Dragicevic, and Sean Follmer.
Zooids: Building Blocks for Swarm User Interfaces. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZVdAfDMP3m0 Video
UIST 2016 - In Proceedings of the 29th Annual Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology, pp. 97-109. ACM, 2016.

Rohit Ashok Khot, Josh Andres, Jennifer Lai, Juerg von Kaenel, and Florian 'Floyd' Mueller.
Fantibles: Capturing Cricket Fan's Story in 3D.
DIS 2016 - In Proceedings of the 2016 ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems, pp. 883-894.

Michael C. Thrun, Florian Lerch, and Jörn Lötsch.
Visualization and 3D Printing of Multivariate Data of Biomarkers.
International Conference in Central Europe on Computer Graphics, Visualization and Computer Vision, 2016.

Tiffany Wun, Jennifer Payne, Samuel Huron, and Sheelagh Carpendale.
Comparing Bar Chart Authoring with Microsoft Excel and Tangible Tiles
EuroVis 2016 - Eurographics Conference on Visualization, 2016.

Fadi Botros, Charles Perin, Bon Adriel Aseniero and Sheelagh Carpendale.
Go and Grow: Mapping Personal Data to a Living Plant.
AVI 2016 - Proceedings of the Working Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces. ACM, 2016.

Trevor Hogan and Eva Hornecker.
Towards a Design Space for Multisensory Data Representation.
Interacting with Computers. Oxford Journals, 2016.

Simon Stusak, Moritz Hobe and Andreas Butz
If Your Mind Can Grasp It, Your Hands Will Help.
TEI 2016 - Proceedings of the 10th International ACM Conference on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction. ACM, 2016

2015

Paul Bourke.
Novel physical representations for the visualisation of science data and mathematics
CGAT 2015 - International Conference on Computer Games, Multimedia & Allied Technology.

Aditya Shekhar Nittala, Nico Li, Stephen Cartwright, Kazuki Takashima, Ehud Sharlin, and Mario Costa Sousa.
PLANWELL: spatial user interface for collaborative petroleum well-planning
SIGGRAPH ASIA 2015 Mobile Graphics and Interactive Applications.

Yvonne Jansen, Pierre Dragicevic, Petra Isenberg, Jason Alexander, Abhijit Karnik, Johan Kildal, Sriram Subramanian, Kasper Hornbæk.
Opportunities and Challenges for Data Physicalization. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_Rst_2i2crg Talk
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2015.

Rohit Ashok Khot, Jeewon Lee, Deepti Aggarwal, Larissa Hjorth, Florian Mueller.
TastyBeats: Designing Palatable Representations of Physical Activity.
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2015.

Moon-Hwan Lee, Seijin Cha, Tek-Jin Nam.
Patina Engraver: Visualizing Activity Logs as Patina in Fashionable Trackers.
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2015.

Bettina Nissen, John Bowers.
Data-Things: Digital Fabrication Situated within Participatory Data Translation Activities.
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2015.

Faisal Taher, John Hardy, Abhijit Karnik, Christian Weichel, Yvonne Jansen, Kasper Hornbæk, Jason Alexander.
Exploring Interactions with Physically Dynamic Bar Charts.
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2015.

Alex S Taylor, Siân E Lindley, Tim Regan, David Sweeney, Vasillis Vlachokyriakos, Lillie Grainger, Jessica Lingel.
Data-in-Place: Thinking through the Relations Between Data and Community.
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2015.

2014

Samuel Huron, Yvonne Jansen, Sheelagh Carpendale.
Constructing Visual Representations: Investigating the Use of Tangible Tokens.
TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, 20(12): 2102-2111, 2014.

Simon Stusak, Aurélien Tabard, Franziska Sauka, Rohit Ashok Khot, Andreas Butz.
Activity sculptures: exploring the impact of physical visualizations on running activity.
TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, 20(12): 2201 - 2210, 2014.

Samuel Huron, Sheelagh Carpendale, Alice Thudt, Anthony Tang, Michael Mauerer.
Constructive Visualization.
DIS2014 - Conference on Designing interactive systems. ACM, New York, NY, USA, 433-442.

Rohit Ashok Khot, Larissa Hjorth, Florian 'Floyd' Mueller.
Understanding physical activity through 3D printed material artifacts.
CHI2014 – Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pages 3835-3844. ACM, 2014.

Saiganesh Swaminathan, Conglei Shi, Yvonne Jansen, Pierre Dragicevic, Lora Oehlberg, Jean-Daniel Fekete.
Supporting the design and fabrication of physical visualizations.
CHI2014 – Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pages 3845-3854. ACM, 2014.

Shaun Kane and Jeffrey Bigham.
Tracking@ stemxcomet: Teaching Programming to Blind Students via 3D Printing, Crisis Management, and Twitter.
SIGCSE '14 - Proceedings of the 45th ACM technical symposium on Computer science education.

2013

Trevor Hogan, and Eva Hornecker.
Blending the repertory grid technique with focus groups to reveal rich design relevant insight.
DPPI 2013 - Designing Pleasurable Products and Interfaces, ACM 2013, 116-125.

Yvonne Jansen and Pierre Dragicevic.
An interaction model for visualizations beyond the desktop.
TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, 19(12): 2396-2405, 2013.

Yvonne Jansen, Pierre Dragicevic, Jean-Daniel Fekete.
Evaluating the efficiency of physical visualizations.
CHI 2013 – Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pages 2593- 2602. ACM, 2013.

2012

Stephen Barrass.
Digital Fabrication of Acoustic Sonifications.
J. Audio Eng. Soc. 60, 9 (2012), 709–715.

Craig Brown and Amy Hurst.
VizTouch: automatically generated tactile visualizations of coordinate spaces.
TEI 2012 - Proceedings of the Sixth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction, pages 131-138, ACM, 2012.

Ian Gwilt, Alaster Yoxall, and Koutaro Sano.
Enhancing the understanding of statistical data through the creation of physical objects.
The 2nd International Conference on Design Creativity (Proceedings). UK, Design Society, pages 117–126, 2012.

Trevor Hogan, and Eva Hornecker.
How does representation modality affect user-experience of data artifacts?
Haptic & Audio Interaction Design, pages 141–151. Springer, 2012.

2010

Andrew Vande Moere, Stephanie Patel.
The Physical Visualization of Information: Designing Data Sculptures in an Educational Context.
Visual Information Communication, pages 1-23. Springer, 2010.

2008

Jack Zhao and Andrew Vande Moere.
Embodiment in Data Sculpture: a Model of the Physical Visualization of Information.
DIMEA 2008 - Proceedings of the 3rd international conference on Digital Interactive Media in Entertainment and Arts, pages 343-350. ACM, 2008.

1998

Michael Bailey, Klaus Schulten and John E Johnson.
The use of solid physical models for the study of macromolecular assembly.
Current Opinion in Structural Biology, 8(2), 202-208.

1997

Dru Clark, Michael Bailey.
Visualization of height field data with physical models and texture photomapping
Proceedings of Visualization '97

Peer-reviewed short papers

2023

* Rick van Loenhout, Champika Ranasinghe, Auriol Degbelo, and Nacir Bouali.  \\ **[[https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3491101.3519638|Physicalizing Sustainable Development Goals Data: An Example with SDG 7 (Affordable and Clean Energy).]]** \\ In Extended Abstracts of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '22). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 346, 1–7. \\ https://doi.org/10.1145/3491101.3519638

2022

Lee Jones, Greta Grip, and Boris Kourtoukov.
The Life of a Building: Machine Knitting a Year of Visitor Data and Online Community Participation During a Pandemic.
In Sixteenth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction (TEI '22). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 80, 1–5.
https://doi.org/10.1145/3490149.3507783

Annika Hinze, Nicholas Vanderschantz, Nicole Sijnja, Bill Rogers, and Sally Jo Cunningham.
Physical Metadata Visualisation: The Knitted Personal Library.
In Sixteenth International Conference on Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction (TEI '22). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 78, 1–7.
https://doi.org/10.1145/3490149.3505582

2020

Schindler, Marwin, Hsiang-Yun Wu, and Renata G. Raidou.
The Anatomical Edutainer.
In 2020 IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS), pp. 1-5. IEEE, 2020.
10.1109/VIS47514.2020.00007.

2018

Maxime Daniel, Guillaume Rivière, and Nadine Couture.
Designing an Expandable Illuminated Ring to Build an Actuated Ring Chart.
TEI 2018 - Proceedings of the 12th International ACM Conference on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction. ACM, 2018

2016

Themis Omirou, Asier Marzo Perez, Sriram Subramanian, and Anne Roudaut.
Floating charts: Data plotting using free-floating acoustically levitated representations
3DUI 2016 - In 2016 IEEE Symposium on 3D User Interfaces, pp. 187-190. IEEE, 2016.

Jonna Häkkilä and Lasse Virtanen.
Physical Items for Visualizing Personal Sleep Data
MobileHCI 2016 - Adjunct, September 06-09, 2016, Florence, Italy

2015

Simon Stusak, Jeannette Schwarz and Andreas Butz.
Evaluating the Memorability of Physical Visualizations.
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM, 2015.

2014

Stephen Barrass.
Acoustic sonification of blood pressure in the form of a singing bowl
Proceedings of the Conference on Sonification in Health and Environmental Data, York University, UK. 2014.

Christian Geiger, Michael Hogen, Jörn Hornig, Michael Schaar.
Datenreise - Digital Bits Made Tangible.
TEI 2014 - Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction, Pages 283-284. ACM, 2014.

Alireza Rezaeian and Jared Donovan.
Design of a Tangible Data Visualization.
VINCI 2014 - Proceedings of the 7th International Symposium on Visual Information Communication and Interaction, pages 232-235. ACM, 2014.

Pepijn Fens and Mathias Funk.
Personal Health Data: Visualization Modalities and Their Perceived Values.
WSCG 2014 - Communication Papers Proceedings, Conference on Computer Graphics, Visualization and Computer Vision. pp. 339-344.

Wiesław Bartkowski.
A physical visualization of a living social network.
Proceedings of the 8th Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction: Fun, Fast, Foundational (NordiCHI '14). ACM NY, USA, 1067–1068.

2013

Trevor Hogan and Eva Hornecker.
In touch with space: embodying live data for tangible interaction.
TEI 2013 - Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction, pages 275-278. ACM, 2013.

2011

Stephen Barrass.
Physical Sonification Dataforms.
ICAD 2011 - The 17th International Conference on Auditory Display, 2011.

2008

Andrew Vande Moere.
Beyond the Tyranny of the Pixel: Exploring the Physicality of Information Visualization.
IV 2008 - Information Visualisation, pages 469 - 474. IEEE, 2008.

2005

Mike Bailey.
Layered Manufacturing for Scientific Visualization (author draft).
Commun. ACM 48, 6 (June 2005), 42-48.

Alexandre Gillet, Michel Sanner, Daniel Stoffler and Arthur Olson.
Tangible Interfaces for Structural Molecular Biology.
Structure, Volume 13, Issue 3, March 2005, Pages 483-491, ISSN 0969-2126.

2004

David Holstius, John Kembel, Amy Hurst, Peng-Hui Wan, Jodi Forlizzi
Infotropism: Living and Robotic Plants as Interactive Displays
DIS 2004 - Conference on Designing Interactive Systems.

2000

David Nadeau and Michael Bailey
Visualizing Volume Data Using Physical Models.
Proceedings of IEEE Visualization 2000 (pp. 497-500).

PhD dissertations

2016

Trevor Hogan
Data Data and Dasein, A Phenomenology of Human-Data Relations.'
PhD thesis, Bauhaus-Universität Weimar, 2016.

Simon Stusak
Exploring the Potential of Physical Visualizations.
PhD thesis, University of Munich, 2 August 2016.

Rohit Ashok Khot
Understanding Material Representations of Physical Activity
PhD thesis, Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology, June 2016.

2014

Yvonne Jansen
Physical and Tangible Information Visualization.
PhD thesis, Université Paris-Sud, 10 March 2014.

Book chapters

2023

Sheelagh Carpendale / Adrien Segal / Alice Thudt / Sarah Hayes / Mieka West / Loren Madsen / Georgia Panagiotidou and Andrew Vand Moere / Pauline Gourlet and Thierry Dassé / Jose Duarte and EasyDataViz / Rimini Protokoll / Domstic Data Streamers / Yvonne Jansen / Stephen Barrass / Ekene Ijeoma / Volker Schweisfurth / MINN_LAB Design Collective / Nick Dulake and Ian Gwilt / Pierre Dragicevic / David Sweeney, Alex Taylor and Siân Lindley / Kim Sauvé and Steven Houben / Nik Hafermaas, Dan Goods and Jamie Barlow / Jason Alexander, Faisal Taher, John Hardy and John Vidler / Mathieu Le Goc, Charles Perin, Sean Follmer, Jean-Daniel Fekete and Pierre Dragicevic / Dietmar Offenhuber / Liina Klauss, Moritz Sefaner, and Skye Morét / Robert Cercós / Dietmar Offenhuber.
see the collection of essays in: Samuel Huron, Till Nagel, Lora Oehlberg, and Wesley Willett. Making with Data: Physical Design and Craft in a Data-Driven World. AK Peters: CRC Press, (2023).

2022

Gwilt, Ian.
See the collection of essays in Making Data: Materializing Digital Information.
Bloomsbury Publishing, 2022.

2021

Pierre Dragicevic, Yvonne Jansen and Andrew Vande Moere
Data Physicalization
In Springer Handbook of Human Computer Interaction, Springer, ISBN 978-3-319-73228-2. In press.

2015

Dietmar Offenhuber and Orkan Telhan.
Indexical Visualization—the Data-Less Information Display.
In Ubiquitous Computing, Complexity and Culture, edited by Ulrik Ekman, Jay David Bolter, Lily Diaz, Morten Søndergaard, and Maria Engberg, 288–303. New York: Routledge.

2013

Ian Gwilt.
Data-Objects: sharing the attributes and properties of digital and material culture to creatively interpret complex information.
In: Digital Media and Technologies for Virtual Artistic Spaces. US, IGI Global, pp. 14-26, 2013.

2012

A. Plohman, M. Sipos (eds.)
Beyond Data.
Baltan Laboratories and Kitchen Budapest 2012

2011

Wolf-Dieter Rase.
Creating Physical 3D Maps Using Rapid Prototyping Techniques.
True-3D in Cartography. Springer.

Extended abstracts

2023

Lora Oehlberg, Wesley Willett, Samuel Huron, Till Nagel, Alice Thudt, Ekene Ijeoma, Dietmar Offenhuber, and Eva Hornecker.
Making with Data (and Beyond). (Panel)
In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '23). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 526, 1–5.

Matthew L. Lee-Smith, Jesse Josua Benjamin, Audrey Desjardins, Mathias Funk, William Odom, Doenja Oogjes, Young-Woo Park, James Pierce, Pedro Sanches, and Vasiliki Tsaknaki.
Data as a Material for Design: Alternative Narratives, Divergent Pathways, and Future Directions. (workshop)
In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '23). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 342, 1–5.

Kim Sauvé, Hans Brombacher, Rosa Van Koningsbruggen, Annemiek Veldhuis, Steven Houben, and Jason Alexander.
Physicalization from Theory to Practice: Exploring Physicalization Design across Domains. (workshop)
In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '23). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 360, 1–7.

2022

Rick van Loenhout, Champika Ranasinghe, Auriol Degbelo, and Nacir Bouali.
Physicalizing Sustainable Development Goals Data: An Example with SDG 7 (Affordable and Clean Energy).
In Extended Abstracts of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '22). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 346, 1–7.
https://doi.org/10.1145/3491101.3519638

2021

Dorsey B. Kaufmann, Nima Hamidi, Kunal Palawat, and Monica Ramirez-Andreotta.
Ripple Effect: Communicating Water Quality Data through Sonic Vibrations.
In Creativity and Cognition (C&C '21).

Maxime Daniel and Guillaume Rivière.: Exploring Axisymmetric Shape-Change’s Purposes and Allure for Ambient Display: 16 Potential Use Cases and a Two-Month Preliminary Study on Daily Notifications. : (WiP) Proc. Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction (TEI '21). ACM NY

He Ren and Eva Hornecker. Comparing Understanding and Memorization in Physicalization and VR Visualization. (WiP) Proc. Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction (TEI '21). ACM NY

2020

Hannes Waldschütz and Eva Hornecker. The Importance of Data Curation for Data Physicalization. (DIS’ 20 Companion), 293–297. Provocations track.

Hannes Waldschütz, Eva Hornecker, Leoni Fischer, Pauline Temme, Anas Alnayef, Sujay Shalawadi, He Ren.
Drum Roll: A Data Physicalization of Real-Time Radiation Sensor Readings. (DIS’ 20 Companion), 477–479. Performance and Design track.

2019

Wannamaker, Kendra, Wesley J. Willett, Lora A. Oehlberg, and Sheelagh Carpendale.
Data embroidery: Exploring alternative mediums for personal physicalization. (poster)

2017

Pauline Gourlet and Thierry Dassé.
Cairn: A Tangible Apparatus for Situated Data Collection, Visualization and Analysis.
DIS 2017 - Proceedings of the 2017 Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (pictorial).

Samuel Huron, Pauline Gourlet, Uta Hinrichs, Trevor Hogan, and Yvonne Jansen.
Let’s Get Physical: Promoting Data Physicalization in Workshop Formats.
DIS 2017 - Proceedings of the 2017 Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (pictorial).

Dan Lockton, Delanie Ricketts, Shruti Aditya Chowdhury and Chang Hee Lee.
Exploring Qualitative Displays and Interfaces.
CHI 2017 - Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems (late-breaking work).

2016

Yun Wang, Xiaojuan Ma, Qiong Luo, and Huamin Qu.
Data Edibilization: Representing Data with Food. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ivfA34fY1rk Talk
CHI 2016 - Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems (alt.chi), pp. 409-422. ACM, 2016.

2015

Stephen Barrass.
Diagnostic singing bowls
ICAD 2015 - Proceedings of the 21st International Conference on Auditory Display.

Chang Long Zhu, Harshit Agrawal, and Pattie Maes.
Data-objects: Re-designing everyday objects as tactile affective interfaces
ACII 2015 - International Conference on Affective Computing and Intelligent Interaction.

Michele Hu.
Exploring New Paradigms for Accessible 3D Printed Graphs.
ASSETS 2015 - Proceedings of the 17th International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers & Accessibility. ACM, 2015.

Tim Regan, David Sweeney, John Helmes, Vasilis Vlachokyriakos, Siân Lindey, and Alex S. Taylor.
Designing Engaging Data in Communities.
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems.

Daniel Buzzo and Nicolo Merendino.
Not all Days are Equal: Investigating the Meaning in the Digital Calendar.
CHI 2015 - Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems.

Tamara Flemisch, Fatemeh Rajabiyazdi, Mona Hosseinkhani Loorak, Sheelagh Carpendale.
NeckLan: Language as Jewellery.
VIS 2015 Posters.

2014

Ken Giang, and Mathias Funk.
Connect-S: A Physical Visualization Through Tangible Interaction.
WSCG 2014 - Poster proceedings of WSCG 2014 Conference on Computer Graphics, Visualization and Computer Vision

Simon Stusak, and Markus Teufel.
Projection augmented physical visualizations.
In Proceedings of the 2nd ACM symposium on Spatial user interaction, pp. 145-145. ACM, 2014.

Simon Stusak, and Ayfer Aslan.
Beyond physical bar charts: an exploration of designing physical visualizations.
CHI 2014 - Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pp. 1381-1386. ACM, 2014.

Steve James Szigeti, Anne Stevens, Robert Tu, Ana Jofre, Alex Gebhardt, Fanny Chevalier, Jonathan Lee, and Sara L. Diamond.
Output to input: concepts for physical data representations and tactile user interfaces.
CHI 2014 - Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pp. 1813-1818. ACM, 2014.

Saiganesh Swaminathan, Conglei Shi, Yvonne Jansen, Pierre Dragicevic, Lora Oehlberg, and Jean-Daniel Fekete.
Creating physical visualizations with makervis.
CHI 2014 - Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 543-546). ACM.

2013

Simon Stusak, Aurélien Tabard, and Andreas Butz.
Can physical visualizations support analytical tasks?
VIS 2013 - Posters of IEEE InfoVis.

Workshop contributions

2023

Kim Sauvé, Hans Brombacher, Rosa van Koningsbruggen, Annemiek Veldhuis, Steven Houben, and Jason Alexander.
Physicalization from Theory to Practice: Exploring Physicalization Design across Domains.
CHI2023. Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. 2018 * Beat Signer, Payam Ebrahimi, Timothy J. Curtin and Ahmed K.A. Abdullah.
Towards a Framework for Dynamic Data Physicalisation.'
Proceedings of the International Workshop 'Toward a Design Language for Data Physicalization' at VIS 2018, Berlin, Germany, October 2018. * Tiffany Wun, Lora Oehlberg, and Sheelagh Carpendale.
Making-With-Data: Supporting DIY Data Physicalizations.
CHI 2018 workshop: Maker Movements, Do-It-Yourself Cultures and Participatory Design: Implications for HCI Research. 2017 * Rahul Bhargava and Catherine D'Ignazio.
Data Sculptures as a Playful and Low-Tech Introduction to Working with Data.'
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Ian Gwilt and Nick Dulake.
Understanding the needs and desires of service users in the design and creation of meaningful physical data representations.
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Sarah Hayes, Trevor Hogan and Kieran Delaney.
Exploring the role Physicalizations can play in STEM Learning.'
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Stéphanie Fleck, Alexis Olry, David Bertolo, Christian Bastien, Robin Vivian and Martin Hachet.
Augmented and Tangible Environments: A Tool for Physicalization of Contents by Children in School Context?
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Jeeeun Kim, Abigale Stangl and Tom Yeh.
Learning Underlying Principles of Physicalization by Tangible, Embodied, and Iterative Fabrication.
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Jörn Hurtienne and Daniel Reinhardt.
Teaching Data Physicalisation to HCI Students – A Case Report.
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Lora Oehlberg.
Hybrid Fabrication of Physicalizations.
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Aubrey Lawson and Eileen Kraemer.
Pedagogy of CS Unplugged: Lessons from Outreach and Education Activities in Computer Science.
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Fearn Bishop and Uta Hinrichs.
Challenges of Running Constructive Visualization Studies with Children.
Extended Abstract for Workshop: Pedagogy & Physicalization: Designing Learning Activities around Physical Data Representations at Designing Interactive Systems Conference (DIS ’17). ACM, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. * Alice Thudt, Uta Hinrichs, and Sheelagh Carpendale.
Data craft: integrating data into daily practices and shared reflections
Workshop 'Quantified Data & Social Relationships' at CHI 2017, Denver, United States. 2016 * Wesley Willett and Samuel Huron.
A Constructive Classroom Exercise for Teaching InfoVis
Workshop 'Innovations in the Pedagogy of Data Visualization' at VIS 2016. * Xin Chen, Jessica Zeitz Self, Leanna House, and Chris North
Be the Data: A New Approach for Immersive Analytics
Workshop on Immersive Analytics at IEEE Virtual Reality 2016. 2015 * See the 15 submissions at the CHI 2015 workshop Exploring the Challenges of Making Data Physical 2014 * Lisa Koeman.
A Personal Visualisation Future: Domestic Data Sculptures
Workshop 'A Personal Perspective on Visualization and Visual Analytics' at DIS 2014 - Conference on Designing interactive systems. ACM, 2014. * Jennifer Payne, Sheelagh Carpendale, Tony Tang.
Physical Visualization and Personal Visual Analytics
Workshop 'A Personal Perspective on Visualization and Visual Analytics' at DIS 2014 - Conference on Designing interactive systems. ACM, 2014. ====== Technical reports ====== 2017 * Beat Signer and Timothy J. Curtin.
Tangible Holograms: Towards Mobile Physical Augmentation of Virtual Objects.**
Technical Report WISE Lab, WISE-2017-01, March 2017.